Guide to the Claude Elliott Texana Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Claude Elliott Texana Collection
1798-1963
1974-001
Elliott, Claude, 1896-1958
4.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This is an artificial and disparate collection of Texana, or materials relating to the history of Texas. In order for the collection to be useful to researchers, an artificial order was imposed by the processor.
Biographical Information:
Claude Elliott (1896-1958) was a historian, university professor and administrator, writer, and collector of Texas history material. He was born in Cross Plains, Texas on September 21, 1896 and grew up and received his early education in Dora, Texas. He attended Abilene Christian College, Simmons College (now Hardin-Simmons University) and West Texas State Teachers College, then served in the United States Navy during World War I. He completed his undergraduate education in 1923, receiving a bachelor of arts degree from Southwest Texas Teachers College (later Southwest Texas State University and now Texas State University). In 1928 he received a master of arts, and in 1934 a doctorate of philosophy, from The University of Texas at Austin, studying under Eugene C. Barker, Charles W. Ramsdell, and Walter P. Webb. Elliott taught school while working on his graduate degrees: he taught history and served as the principal at Donna High School, served as superintendent of the La Feria school system, and taught history at UT. In 1927 he married Emma Edwin Moore of San Marcos.
Elliot held a number of positions at Southwest Texas State University. He was professor of history 1929 to 1942, registrar and director of personnel 1942 to 1949, coordinator of veteran affairs 1943 to 1945, and the first dean of graduate studies 1949 to 1958. He was a member of a number of historical organizations, including the Texas State Historical Association, the Mississippi Valley Historical Association, the Texas State Teachers Association, and the Classroom Teachers Association. Elliott was a fellow of the Texas State Historical Association, serving as vice-president 1947 to 1952 and president 1953 to 1955. He was a member of the advisory council and a major contributor to the first two volumes of the Handbook of Texas.
His publications include Leathercoat: The Life History of a Texas Patriot (1938), and Theses on Texas History (1955). Texas: Wilderness to Space Age was published posthumously in 1962 by his wife and Dr. William Pool of Southwest Texas State University. Elliott’s articles were published in the Southwestern Historical Quarterly, the Georgia Historical Review, the Southwestern Social Science Quarterly (now the Social Science Quarterly), and the Journal of Southern History.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings (information artifacts); Diaries; Financial records; Government records; Legal documents; Letters (correspondence); Scrapbooks; Sheet music; Speeches (documents)
Geographic Name:
Texas -- History; Texas -- History -- 1846-1950; Texas -- History -- 1951-; Texas -- History -- Revolution, 1835-1836; Texas -- History -- To 1846
Personal Name:
Ferguson, James Edward, 1871-1944; Ferguson, Miriam Amanda, 1875-1961; Sterling, Ross S., 1875-1949
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This is an artificial and disparate collection of Texana, or materials relating to the history of Texas. In order for the collection to be useful to researchers, an artificial order was imposed by the processor. The collection is divided into seven series: Pre-Republic (to 1836); Republic (1836-1845); Annexation and Early Statehood (1845-1860); Civil War and Expansion (1861-1901); Modern Statehood (1901-1956); Claude Elliott Papers; and Governors Ferguson/Sterling Papers. Series, sub-series, and folder titles have been standardized as much as possible. The first five series, directly relating to Texas history, each contain the same three sub-series: Documents, Printed Material, and Creative Works. Folders are arranged in alphabetical order and items within the folders are arranged chronologically.
The standardized folder titles are fairly broad in order to accommodate the varied nature of the collection. In general, a folder entitled Land will contain deeds; a folder entitled Legal will contain miscellaneous items such as wills and probate documents, indentures, and promissory notes; and a folder entitled Government will contain sheriff’s documents and gubernatorial appointments to local offices. In a few instances, such as with the Annexation of Texas, the amount and focus of the material warrants a specific folder title.
In some instances, items from the twentieth century, such as newspaper or periodical articles, have been placed in an earlier series if the information pertains to an event or person in an earlier period. For example, twentieth century articles on brands have been placed with the nineteenth century brand book.
Some material in the collection was owned previously by Dr. Alexander Dienst, Jr. (1870-1938) of Temple, Texas, a historian and collector of Texana. His handwritten notes and commentary appear on some of the items. He was a friend and supporter of Governor James E. Ferguson.
Detailed List of Contents
- Pre-Republic (to 1836)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Texas materials from the time of Spanish and Mexican rule. The majority of the series comprises manuscripts relating to land, including some written in Spanish.
  - Documents
    - Government, 1826-1835 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Land, 1825-1835 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Legal, 1825-1835 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Spanish, 1798-1835 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Freemasonry and Texas History, 1800-1835 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
      Typescript of (and correspondence regarding) a presentation made to the Texas State Historical Association, April 25, 1952.
  - Printed Material
    - History, 1832-1835 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Creative Works
    - Poetry, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Republic (1836-1845)
  Items in this series pertain to Texas as an independent republic. Items of interest include a promissory note to Mirabeau B. Lamar, president of the Republic; an early Land Book of Texas; a Gonzales County Probate book; a journal by early Texan Ammon Underwood; Colonel Pedro Delgado’s account of the battle of San Jacinto; and accounts of early Texans Peter Gallagher and Robert Potter.
  - Documents
    - Financial, 1836-1842 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Government, 1837-1845 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Land, 1836-1844 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Legal, 1836-1845 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters, 1838-1844 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Military, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Land - Land Book of Texas, 1838 (Ovs box 1, Folder 1)
    - Legal - Gonzalez County Probate book, 1838-1845 (Ovs box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printed Material
    - Government, 1836-1838 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - History, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Creative Works
    - Journals/Memoirs (typed transcriptions), 1834-1838 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
    - Music, 1822-1836 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Poetry, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Journals/Memoirs - Ammon Underwood journal (photostat copy), 1834-1838 (Ovs box 1, Folder 3)
- Annexation and Early Statehood (1845-1860)
  This series contains material relating to the early years of Texas statehood. Items of interest include gubernatorial appointments to local offices, and a Bell County Official Bonds book. Folder 33 contains a document of Public Sale of Land and Negroes dated 1858.
  - Documents
    - Education, 1855-1859 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Financial, 1852-1860 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Government, 1850-1860 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Land, 1847-1860 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Legal, 1847-1860 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Letters, 1847-1860 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Government - Bell County Official Bonds book, 1850-1851 (Ovs box 1, Folder 4)
    - Land - land grant, 1847 (Ovs box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material
    - Annexation of Texas, 1844-1845 (Box 1, Folder 28-30)
    - Business, 1853-1860 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Education, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Government, 1854-1860 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - History, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Military, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Creative Works
    - Music, 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Poetry, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Civil War and Expansion (1861-1901)
  This series contains material pertaining to Texas in the last half of the nineteenth century. Items of interest include three Bell County Stock books and a Bell County Marks and Brands book in two sections; Caldwell County teachers’ paychecks; a book of Bell County taxpayers; a Texas Veterans Association scrapbook; and three copies of the diary of John Lafayette Lane, a Confederate soldier and prospector. One particularly noteworthy item is “A Declaration of the Causes which impel the State of Texas to Secede from the Federal Union” from 1861 (in Sub-Series 2, Box 2, Folder 7).
  - Documents
    - Agriculture, 1858-1900 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Education, 1885-1887 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - Financial, 1870-1897 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Government, 1863-1900 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Land, 1862-1900 (Box 1, Folder 43-50)
    - Legal, 1861-1889 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Letters, 1861-1900 (Box 1, Folder 52-53)
    - Military, 1862-1870 (Box 1, Folder 54-55)
    - Promissory Notes, 1862-1887 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Tax Receipts, 1859-1898 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Agriculture - three Bell County Stock books; Bell County Marks and Brands book; Bell County Alliance book, 1858-1901 (Ovs box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - Land - Bell County Taxpayers book, 1895 (Ovs box 2, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material
    Of particular note in this sub-series is an item in Folder 7: an eight-page pamphlet from 1861 titled “A Declaration of the Causes which impel the State of Texas to Secede from the Federal Union.”
    - Agriculture – Texas Cooperative Association/Patrons of Husbandry, 1878-1898 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Business, 1873-1898 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
    - Confederacy, 1864-1865 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes “A Declaration of the Causes which impel the State of Texas to Secede from the Federal Union,” 1861.
    - Education, 1895-1896 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Government, 1863-1893 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Government - Speeches, 1877-1886 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - History, 1867-1893 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Local Government, 1877-1899 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Maps, Texas, 1861-1882 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Military, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Political, 1884-1892 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Religious, 1888-1897 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Patterns - Young Ladies Journal Supplements, 1886-1891 (Ovs box 3, Folder 4)
  - Creative Works
    - Journals/Memoirs/Ledger, 1850-1865 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Music, 1880s (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Photographs/Portraits/Drawings, 1861-1865 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Poetry, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Journals/Memoirs/Ledger - John Lafayette Lane diary; Edward Tourfax journal (photostat copy), 1850-1865 (Ovs box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Journals/Memoirs/Ledger - John Lafayette Lane diary; Edward Tourfax journal (typed transcription), 1850-1865 (Ovs box 2, Folder 9)
    - Journals/Memoirs/Ledger - Edward Tourfax journal, 1850-1865 (Ovs box 2, Folder 10)
    - Music - Mexican and American, 1880s (Ovs box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - Photographs/Portraits/Drawings - ink drawing of Texas State Capital, 1888 (Ovs box 2, Folder 13)
    - Scrapbook, Texas Veterans Association, 1882-1891 (Ovs box 2, Folder 14)
- Modern Statehood (1901-1963)
  Material in this series concerns the modern state of Texas, beginning in 1901 with the discovery of oil at Spindletop. Items of note include issues of the Congressional Record that pertain to Texas; speeches given by Texas legislators; and an incomplete run of the War Information Series. An item of note is a signed letter from then-Senator Lyndon B. Johnson to Judge C.V. Terrell, dated in 1956 (in Sub-Series 1, Box 2, Folder 22).
  - Documents
    - Letters, 1901-1956 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Letters and Roster of Initiates for the Beneficent Order of the Red Red Rose, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 22a)
  - Printed Material
    - Agriculture, 1919-1944 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Business, 1939-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Education, 1901-1956 (Box 2, Folder 25-29)
    - Government - Congressional Record, 1925-1941 (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Government - Speeches, 1906-1953 (Box 2, Folder 33-39)
    - Government - War Information Series, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
    - History, 1905-1963 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Local Government, 1911-1956 (Box 2, Folder 43-45)
    - Military, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Political, 1918-1952 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Religious, 1921-1951 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - History - Killeen Herald Newspaper; John Nance Garner Souvenir Postcard, 1905-1958 (Ovs box 3, Folder 1)
  - Creative Works
    - Photograph/Slide, 1913-1943 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Poetry, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Claude Elliott Papers
  This series contains some of Claude Elliott’s scholarship, including entries he wrote for the Handbook of Texas, offprints from journals, and miscellaneous research material.
  - Bibliographies (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Handbook of Texas, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Handbook of Texas Entries, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript Fragments/Research Material, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Offrprints/Disbounds, 1947-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Governors Ferguson/Sterling Papers
  Items in this series pertain to three early twentieth century Texas governors, James E. and Miriam A. Ferguson, and Ross Sterling. Some of the political items, such as newspaper articles, reference both the Fergusons and Sterling. Of special interest is a holograph diary of James E. Ferguson and letters written by him.
  - James E. Ferguson, Governor, 1915-1917
    - Financial - American National Bank, Austin, 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Financial - Bastrop Lignite Coal Company, 1916-1920 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Financial, 1914-1921 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Letters by, 1914-1932 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - Letters by, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Letters to or about, 1916-1923 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Political, 1914-1924 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
    - Financial - Temple State Bank Book; two sheets holograph financials, 1917-1921. Political - Campaign Material, 1914-1917 (Ovs box 3, Folder 1)
    - Diary, 1937 (Ovs box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miriam A. Ferguson, Governor, 1925-1926, 1933-1934
    - Letters, 1917-1925 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Political, 1924-1940 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    - Political - Speech, 1940 (Ovs box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ross Sterling, Governor, 1931-1933
    - Political, 1931-1933 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Political - Campaign Material, 1932 (Ovs box 3, Folder 1)